<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some reflections on a late pamphlet entituled, A vindication of Their Majesties authority to fill the sees of the deprived bishops, &amp;c in a letter from the city to a friend in the country.</title>
            <author>Browne, Thomas, 1654?-1741.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12265445</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12265445</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58049</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58049)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 56:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some reflections on a late pamphlet entituled, A vindication of Their Majesties authority to fill the sees of the deprived bishops, &amp;c in a letter from the city to a friend in the country.</title>
                  <author>Browne, Thomas, 1654?-1741.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Browne, B.D., Fellow of St. Johns College, Cambridge.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.); BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699. --  Vindication of Their Majesties authority to fill the sees of the deprived bishops.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58049:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME REFLECTIONS ON A LATE PAMPHLET, Entituled, A VINDICATION OF Their Majeſties Authority TO FILL THE SEES OF THE DEPRIVED BISHOPS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Letter from the City to a Friend in the Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58049:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58049:2"/>
            <head>SOME REFLECTIONS ON A LATE Pamphlet, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Account which you receiv'd in the Country of Dr. <hi>B—'s Refuſal of the Biſhoprick of</hi> Bath <hi>and</hi> Wells, hath not perhaps occaſioned a greater <hi>Talk,</hi> and lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Noiſe</hi> with you, than the ſevere Cenſures and Reflections on him have here for ſuch his Refuſal; and the <hi>Noiſe</hi> is not a little increaſed by a <hi>Pamphlet</hi> newly come out under the Stamp of <hi>Authority.</hi> In which the <hi>Author</hi> has given perhaps no leſs an <hi>unhappy Amuſement, to which a wiſe Man, who had well conſidered Conſequences, would not have given the Occaſion.</hi> For why muſt Dr. <hi>B</hi>—be ſo ſeverely Cenſur'd and Reflected on for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing a Biſhoprick? Is he not <hi>ſui Juris,</hi> at his own diſpoſe? Has he not the Liberty of his Will? May he not act and govern himſelf, in inſtances of Choice or Refuſal, according to his own Inclination? Is the refuſing of a Biſhoprick ſuch an unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Crime, and of ſuch dangerous and fatal Conſequence, that it ſhakes and diſturbs the Government, and threatens to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58049:3"/> it, and <hi>unſettle the Minds of Men?</hi> Was a Biſhoprick never refus'd before? Are there no Inſtances of it in former Reigns? Were there not ſome that refus'd Biſhopricks in the Reigns of King <hi>Charles</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> and yet little Notice taken of it, and no Fears entertain'd of any <hi>miſchievous Effects</hi> conſequent to ſuch a Refuſal? And what <hi>miſchievous Effects</hi> ſhould our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> be apprehenſive of now, upon the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Refuſal, unleſs ſuch as the Gentlemen of the High-way, who have taken a Purſe, are jealous of from one of their Fellows, who ſullenly refuſes his ſhare of the <hi>Dividend;</hi> whom therefore they are juſtly angry with, ſuſpecting that he will betray 'em, and be an Inſtrument to reſtore the Plunder to the good Man, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf a Pardon for that piece of Juſtice, and effectual Repentance?</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author</hi> tells us, Pag, 2. <hi>he can eaſily apprehend ſeveral Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which might move wiſe and good Men rather to chuſe an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Preferment, void by Death or Ceſſion, than by Deprivation.</hi> And why will he not allow Dr. <hi>B</hi>—to be one of thoſe <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>good Men,</hi> whoſe Head perhaps is as clear, and his Eyes as open to apprehend thoſe Reaſons?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But,</hi> it ſeems, <hi>our preſent Circumſtances are ſuch, as ought to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule all Niceties—i. e.</hi> to go through Stitch with the Work, Right or Wrong; to go on, to preſs forward through Thick and Thin, over Shoes, over Boots; to curb the Struggles of the reluctant Mind, and ſilence the upbraiding Clamours and Crys of Conſcience, which muſt not be ſo rude and unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as not to give place, <hi>in our Circumſtances,</hi> to the louder Voice, and more prevalent Arguments of <hi>Intereſt: The Miſchiefs of ſuch a Refuſal being ſo intolerable, as nothing can excuſe, much leſs juſtifie it, but the abſolute Unlawfulneſs of ſucceeding in ſuch Preferments, while the Deprived Biſhop lives.</hi>—</p>
            <p>And what if the <hi>Doctor</hi> is convinced of the <hi>Unlawfulneſs</hi> of it, that I hope may <hi>excuſe,</hi> if not <hi>juſtifie,</hi> his <hi>Refuſal.</hi> Which though our <hi>Author</hi> thinks <hi>very odd for them to pretend, who have ſubmitted to the preſent Government,</hi> yet perhaps the <hi>Doctor</hi> is of another Opinion, who, it may be, is not ſo thorough-pac'd and zealous
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58049:3"/> a Conformiſt, as implicitly to ſubſcribe to, and comply with whatſoever the preſent Governours ſhall command and direct.</p>
            <p>And then our <hi>Author</hi> advances, Pag. 3. <hi>to conſider the firſt ſort of Reaſons;</hi> which yet, he ſays, <hi>are no Reaſons in our Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces—i. e.</hi> ſay what you will, and offer what Reaſons you can, they are all unreaſonable in compariſon of the great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Argument of <hi>Intereſt;</hi> which to ſubmit to now, <hi>in our Circumſtances,</hi> there is an abſolute and indiſpenſable <hi>NECES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SITY;</hi> the great and mighty Argument, and <hi>BURDEN</hi> of the famous <hi>PASTORAL,</hi> tun'd <hi>ad uſum SARUM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As to the firſt,</hi> ſays he, <hi>it may ſo happen, that the Perſon deprived, and the Perſon to be promoted, have been old and intimate Friends; and this may grate hard upon the Perſon to be promoted, to ſucceed in the Chair of one whom he loves, whoſe Misfortunes he pities,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is juſt like the Caſe of an <hi>Oliverian</hi> Sequeſtrator, who came to enter upon the Eſtate of his <hi>old and intimate Friend,</hi> which he enter'd on with ſome Reluctancy and Concern; <hi>It gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hard upon him</hi> to ſequeſter the Eſtate of <hi>one whom he lov'd, whoſe Misfortune he pitied, whom he greatly valued for his other many good Qualities</hi>—But he is a Malignant, and therefore muſt be ſequeſtred. <hi>Now,</hi> ſays the Sequeſtrator, <hi>if to refuſe ſuch</hi> an Eſtate, or <hi>Preferment, could keep my Friend poſſeſſed of it, there were ſome ſenſe in this; but I know no other caſe, whereen 'tis thought a breach of Friendſhip to ſucceed a Friend in</hi> an Eſtate or <hi>Preferment which he has loſt, and which the Law ſays is not, and ſhall not be his, when there is no foul play in ſupplanting him, any more than to ſucceed a dead Friend: Friendſhip is ſo far from being any Reaſon againſt it, that it ſhould make it deſirable to both; to one, That his Friend might get what he has loſt; to the other, That he may have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, if there be occaſion for it, to make his Friend's Misfortune more eaſy than a Stranger would do.</hi> Which is juſt like the Apology that the more civil, better natur'd Thief makes for taking the good Man's Purſe, who, he tells you, might have fallen into the hands of an ungenteeler Robber, who perhaps would have dealt roughly and rudely with him, and have made his <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune</hi> ſo much the more <hi>uneaſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58049:4"/>
            <p>But our <hi>Author</hi> demands, Pag. 5. <hi>If Friendſhip be no Objection, what ſhould hinder any Man from taking a Preferment which another is Legally deprived of? For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I muſt take the Legality of it for granted now, and argue upon that Suppoſition.</hi> But he takes that for granted which is diſputed, and that by not a few of the <hi>Swearers</hi> themſelves, who, I believe, are not ſatisfied in all Points as to the Juſtice and Legality of the <hi>Revolution,</hi> and all Things that are done in it. What elſe is the meaning of the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> (which ſtands yet upon Record) of ſome of the Members of the <hi>Convention</hi> againſt the <hi>Vacancy,</hi> who might as well and as juſtly proteſt againſt the Vacancy of the <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> as that of the <hi>Royal Throne,</hi> each being made and declar'd Vacant by the ſame Authority. If the Proceedings were thought Legal, why was the Word <hi>Rightful</hi> in the firſt Draught of the new Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance ſo violently oppos'd, and at laſt razed out? If the <hi>New King</hi> was not <hi>Rightful King,</hi> he was not Legally King, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an <hi>Uſurper;</hi> and conſequently all that was done by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and the Authority of the <hi>Convention</hi> that made him <hi>King,</hi> is illegal. If they were thoroughly convinc'd of the Legality of the <hi>Revolution,</hi> why did ſo many, who have taken the <hi>New Oaths,</hi> refuſe to take them in the Senſe of the Impoſers, but their own, and invent <hi>New Salvoes</hi> to quiet their ſtruggling and reluctant Conſciences? Some declaring, that they took the Oath only as <hi>an Obligation to live peaceably;</hi> others, with a Proviſo, <hi>that it did not oppoſe, contradict, or annul, the Ancient Fundamental Laws of this Realm:</hi> Others were drawn by the Magnetick Force, and influenced by the powerful Charms of that rare, new-invented <hi>Salvo,</hi> that ſuperfine <hi>Criticiſm</hi> of a certain eminent <hi>Divine,</hi> and eloquent <hi>Preacher</hi> in this City, (than which the ſubtle, moſt <hi>Ariſtoteletotical Thomas Aquinas</hi> himſelf could not have invented a better) <hi>viz. That the taking the New Oath is only a temporary Suſpenſion of Allegiance to King JAMES; to whom, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, we might warrantably return to our Duty and Allegiance.</hi> A ſmooth and lucky Vehicle, which tempted not a few <hi>young Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks</hi> to ſwallow the <hi>bitter Pill.</hi>—So that the <hi>Legality</hi> of the <hi>Revolution,</hi> and conſequently of the <hi>Deprivation,</hi> being
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58049:4"/> queſtion'd and diſprov'd, our <hi>Author</hi> proceeds upon a wrong Hypotheſis; and has little Reaſon to blame Dr. <hi>B</hi>—for refuſing a Preferment, which to take, being <hi>another</hi>'s, is utterly unlawful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But there is a more material Conſideration,</hi> ſays our <hi>Author,</hi> pag. 6. <hi>which may influence prudent and cautious Men, who are well preferred already. The Experience of the Revolution in 1660. hath taught them how dangeroas it may be in caſe ſuch a Revolution ſhould happen, to change their old Preferments for new ones, which may be challenged again by their old Proprietors.</hi> And why is our <hi>Author</hi> angry with ſuch <hi>prudent</hi> and <hi>cautious Men,</hi> who are ſo tractable as to be willing to be taught by the woful Experience and ſad Examples of others, who fooliſhly unhing'd themſelves, and quitted their <hi>old</hi> for a precarious Title to <hi>new Preferments,</hi> which, <hi>currente Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ,</hi> were juſtly challenged again by their <hi>old Proprietors?</hi> Why may they not be allowed to learn Wiſdom from the burnt Child, which dreads the Fire, and from the cheated Dog in the Fable, whoſe Folly was ſufficiently chaſtis'd by ſnapping at the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</p>
            <q>—Felix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</q>
            <p>But why does our <hi>Author</hi> ſo much dread, Why does he put ſo acute an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of Horror upon <hi>SUCH</hi> a <hi>Revolution,</hi> as was that of 1660. which every 29th. of <hi>May,</hi> the Anniverſary Commemoration of it, does bleſs; and <hi>all Generations ſhall call it bleſſed:</hi> It being a <hi>Revolution</hi> which brought many ineſtimable Bleſſings with it: Which ſtanch'd the Flux of Blood, clos'd our ghaſtly gaping Wounds, and heal'd our Breaches, and put an End to our miſerable Confuſions, and the <hi>Great Rebellion:</hi> Which crown'd us with the deſirable, long wiſh'd for Bleſſings of Peace and Plenty; and reſtor'd to every Man his Right; to the <hi>King</hi> his Crown and Royal Dignity, to the <hi>Church</hi> her Revenues and Liturgy, to the <hi>State</hi> the courſe of Juſtice and Deliverance from Slavery, to the poor oppreſſed, ſequeſtred, Loyal <hi>Engliſh Subject</hi> his Liberty and Property, and to theſe <hi>diſtracted Nations</hi> a happy Settlement, and an opulent Proſperity: <hi>A Revolution</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58049:5"/> which was not <hi>like the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">With ſuch invidious Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters there were not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome, like our <hi>Author,</hi> to diſgrace, to overcaſt the brighter Dawn of that <hi>happy Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupy and prejudice the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nds of Men.</note> 
               <hi>breaking in of the Sea to overthrow our Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and cauſe us <hi>to periſh with our Neighbours;</hi> but like the ſoft and gentle Dew, or joyful Rain to the parched Earth, to refreſh and comfort it. And why ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld our <hi>Author</hi> be ſo much afraid of, and ſo vehemently deprecate <hi>SUCH</hi> a <hi>Revolution;</hi> unleſs he has chang'd his <hi>Old Preferments</hi> for <hi>New ones,</hi> which he may juſtly fear will be <hi>challenged again by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Proprieters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am confident were the Generality of the <hi>Engliſh Subjects</hi> (how much ſoever they are prejudic'd now, being too apt to be blinded by the Vapours of intoxicating <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi>) ſatisfied that another would prove <hi>SUCH</hi> a <hi>Revolution,</hi> as was that of 1660. (which they have the leſs cauſe to fear, conſidering that the <hi>Perſon</hi> to be <hi>reſtored</hi> is not a cruel bloody <hi>Nero,</hi> or <hi>Diocletian,</hi> but a <hi>Branch of the forgiving Race,</hi> related to the <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Charles the Merciful,</hi> and an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> born; to which may be added the ſignal Inſtances of his Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and forbearing Mercy in <hi>Ireland</hi> (to the great diſguſt and diſſatisfaction of the <hi>French</hi> Generals) when he might have taken (in all likelihood, ſucceſsful) Advantage over the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, when in a ſick, and weak, and languid State; whom he pitied, as a true <hi>Father</hi> of his Country) I am confident, I ſay, that from <hi>SUCH</hi> a <hi>Revolution</hi> they would not make it their Litany, <hi>Libera nos Domine;</hi> or cry out in a Fright, at the apprehenſion of it, in the Language of our <hi>Author, If there ever be SUCH a Revolution, &amp;c. God be merciful to this miſerable Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our <hi>Author</hi> makes a lamentable Complaint, Pag. 9. <hi>What an unpardonable Scandal Dr.</hi> B—'<hi>s Refuſal hath given both to the Enemies and the Friends of the Government.</hi>—Which, by the way, is no very good Argument of the Goodneſs of it, and no very lucky <hi>Omen</hi> or <hi>Prognoſtick</hi> of its <hi>Stability</hi> or <hi>Continuance:</hi> In as much as in former <hi>Reigns</hi> the like Refuſal has not given ſuch a <hi>Scandal,</hi> as our <hi>Author</hi> ſpeaks of. Which does not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and neceſſarily owe it ſelf to the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Refuſal, though accidentally and occaſionally it may, but to the ſick, and lame, and tottering State of the <hi>Government,</hi> which really is neither
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58049:5"/> made better nor worſe, neither ſtrengthened nor weakened by the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Refuſal. But his refuſing to be made ſo eminent a Member of it, and that either out of Fear, or Conſcience, or both, may accidentally ſuggeſt Reflections upon the <hi>Stability</hi> or Authority of it. And if <hi>this confirms the Enemies of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their Opinion of the Unlawfulneſs to ſubmit to it, and weakens the hands of Friends, and makes them cautious of embarking in a ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Intereſt, and fills them with new Jealouſies of the Lawfulneſs of it,</hi> who can help it, whom may we thank for it? Not the <hi>Doctor,</hi> but the <hi>Badneſs</hi> of the Cauſe, which as the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Refuſal could not make worſe, ſo his Compliance cannot make better.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph, Pag. 10. we find our <hi>Author</hi> in a great Fright, <hi>dreading what might be the fatal Conſequence of ſuch a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage as this both to Church and State: i. e.</hi> I preſume leaſt it ſhould tempt and provoke the <hi>new Governours</hi> to alter the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſet up Presbytery. But then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently his Fears vaniſh, being <hi>perſuaded of the good Inclinations of their Majeſties to the Church of</hi> England; of which indeed they have given a ſignal Evidence by their <hi>wonderful</hi> kindneſs to the <hi>Epiſcopal Members</hi> of the <hi>Church of</hi> Scotland. But this our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>'s Eyes are not yet open to ſee, being blinded and tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſome of that extatick <hi>Zeal and good Affection,</hi> which his <hi>wiſer Men</hi> (Pag. 11.) are inſpired with, which perhaps was the cauſe of that unmannerly Effort, that inſtance of Rudeneſs and Folly in him, of calling the <hi>Doctor</hi> Fool, which <hi>is the ſoftest Name</hi> that his good Breeding could beſtow upon him, which I am apt to think was a little too rude treating of ſo <hi>Reverend</hi> a Perſon, whom the Government thought worthy of ſo high a Character, had he not been too ſelf-denying to accept of it.</p>
            <p>He then proceeds in the next Paragraph, Pag. 11, 12. to his Concluſion from the Premiſſes. <hi>This,</hi> ſays he, <hi>plainly proves, that ſuppoſing it Lawful to have taken the Biſhoprick, no other Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whatſoever can juſtify the Refuſal in our Circumſtances</hi>—If then, according to his own Argument, it be unlawful, or if the <hi>Doctor</hi> thought it ſo, his <hi>Refuſal</hi> is juſtifiable. But he <hi>knows not how to ſuppoſe that the</hi> Doctor <hi>could think it unlawful.</hi> Which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58049:6"/> that he could not do, he endeavours to prove by two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p>The firſt is drawn from the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Submiſſion to the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and taking <hi>the Oaths of Allegiance as early as any Man, and never</hi> that our <hi>Author</hi> heard <hi>had the leaſt Scruple about it.</hi> (Pag. 12) Perhaps the <hi>Doctor</hi> took the Oath as ſome of the Kentiſh Clergy took it—<hi>i. e.</hi> as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did eat <hi>Manna, to keep 'em from ſtarving.</hi> But perhaps the <hi>Doctor</hi> repents, and ſees his Error, and is ſorry for what he has done, and therefore as a true Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, will not add Sin to Sin. And though he took the new Oath of Allegiance, and that perhaps a little too precipitantly, yet he will not <hi>Rob,</hi> or <hi>Steal,</hi> nor commit <hi>Sacriledge.</hi> But our <hi>Author</hi> is very uncharitable, and will allow <hi>no place for Repentance,</hi> though, as <hi>Eſau,</hi> a Man <hi>ſeek it carefully with Tears. For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>this was the time to have been Scrupulous, if he would have been ſo; for it ſeems a little of the lateſt, when he is become a ſworn Subject to K.</hi> William <hi>and Q.</hi> Mary <hi>to queſtion their Authority to make a Biſhop.</hi> But if true Repentance be not too late with God, I know not why Man ſhould account it ſo.</p>
            <p>His ſecond Argument is drawn, Pag. 13. from the <hi>Doctor's exerciſing Archi-Epiſcopal Authority, by Commiſſien from the Dean and Chapter of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>during the Vacancy of the See, by the Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the A. B. as it is expreſſed in the Commiſſion—And this,</hi> he tells us, <hi>he takes to be altogether as unlawful (if either of them were unlawful) to ſeiſe upon the Authority of the A. B. upon the Account of his Deprivation, as to take the Character, and exerciſe the Authority of a Biſhop in the See of a deprived Biſhop.</hi> Let the <hi>Doctor</hi> anſwer for this himſelf, as I doubt not <hi>ſo great a Canoniſt</hi> is able to do: Though at the firſt ſight it appears to any one that is not ſo well vers'd and learned in the Canon Law, that to exerciſe <hi>Archi Epiſcopal Authority,</hi> when the <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi>'s hands were tyed up, and could not do it himſelf, is a leſs Fault than to enter, <hi>pleno Jure,</hi> upon the Right and Poſſeſſion of a Biſhop, <hi>unjuſtly deprived,</hi> and ſeiſe, and enjoy the Revenues of his <hi>See.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58049:6"/>
            <p>But I cannot but obſerve how induſtriouſly and malitiouſly our <hi>Author</hi> (like the Great <hi>Abaddon</hi>) endeavours to keep the poor <hi>Doctor</hi> from Repentance, by ſhewing and expoſing the Abſurdity and Unreaſonableneſs of his Refuſal, from this Conſideration, That he has plung'd himſelf ſo deeply in one Act after another, in compliance with the Government, (which is ſuppos'd to confirm his Opinion of the Lawfulneſs of it) that he cannot now Stop, but muſt go on <hi>ad Finem uſque.</hi> Alas! what a <hi>Dilemma</hi> do Men bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when they go out of God's Way, and leave the Paths of <hi>Truth, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs!</hi> He that makes one falſe Step, knows not whither he may wander. He that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly commits one Error, knows not when, or where he ſhall end.</p>
            <q>Uno Abſurdo dato ſequuntur Mille.</q>
            <p>But this is the Sinner's Comfort amidſt the frightful View of his repeated Acts of Sin, that ſincere Repentance will expiate for his greateſt Errors, reſolving, <hi>If I have done Evil, I will do ſo no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus our <hi>Author</hi> having endeavour'd to prove that the <hi>Doctor</hi> could not think it <hi>unlawful</hi> to take the <hi>Biſhoprick;</hi> He tells us, Pag. 14. what the Peoples Sentiments are of his <hi>Refuſal: Which,</hi> ſays he, <hi>after an appearing forwardneſs to take it, hath tempted People to think, that he judges it unlawful.</hi> And if they do ſo, our <hi>Author</hi> has put a very fine Argument in their Mouths by an eaſy Train of neceſſary <hi>Conſequences</hi> (wherein he ſpeaks great Truths, perhaps againſt his Will) which may be more diſſerviceable to the <hi>Government</hi> than he is aware of; the bare Recital of which will be enough with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Comment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If,</hi> ſays he, (Pag. 15.) <hi>it be unlawful</hi> (and perhaps not only the <hi>Doctor,</hi> but others beſides him think ſo) <hi>to ſucceed a deprived Biſhop, then he is the Biſhop of the Dioceſe ſtill; and then the Law that deprives him is no Law, and conſequently the King
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58049:7"/> and Parliament, that made that Law, no King nor Parliament</hi>—Which indeed ſome have been ſo bold to queſtion, thinking it hardly poſſible that that can be a <hi>lawful King,</hi> who was made ſo by the <hi>People;</hi> or that a <hi>lawful Parliament,</hi> which was cut out of a <hi>Convention,</hi> not ſummon'd by the King's Writs, but made a <hi>Parliament</hi> by the celebrated Miracle of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> A true Jeſt perhaps. But <q>
                  <l>—Ridentem dicere Verum</l>
                  <l>Quis vetat?—</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But to go on with his admirable Train of Deductions, (Pag. 15.) <hi>If,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the deprived Biſhop be the only lawful Biſhop, then the People and Clergy of his Dioceſe are bound to own him and no other; then all the Biſhops who own the Authority of a New Arch-Biſhop, and live in Communion with him, are Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks; and the Clergy, who live in Communion with Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Biſhops, are Schiſmaticks themſelves; and the whole Church of</hi> England <hi>now Establiſhed by</hi> [the New] <hi>Law is Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, and Dr.</hi> B—<hi>himſelf a Schiſmatick, if he communicate with it. And thus we have no Church, or only a Schiſmatical Church, as well as no King; and all that Dr.</hi> B—<hi>has got by refuſing a Biſhoprick, is to prove himſelf a Schiſmatick, if he live in Communion; or to make a Schiſm, if he Separate from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>—The laſt Branch of his Disjunction I deny: For though Dr. <hi>B</hi>——proves himſelf a <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> if he live in Communion with a <hi>Schiſmatical Church,</hi> yet he does not make a <hi>Schiſm</hi> by ſeparating from it. For he makes the <hi>Schiſm,</hi> who makes the Terms of Communion unlawful. And, by the way, if all is true in this Train of Conſequences, neither our <hi>Author,</hi> I hope, nor his <hi>ſwearing Brethren,</hi> will be offended at, or condemn the <hi>New Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I paſs to his ſecond Head of Diſcourſe, Pag. 17. <hi>viz. the Lawfulneſs of the Thing it ſelf; which,</hi> he ſays, <hi>is ſo evident when ſet in a clear Light that it will admit of no Diſpute with Men of Senſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58049:7"/>
            <p>He tells us, That <hi>in a late Letter ſaid to be ſent to Dr.</hi> B—<hi>and now printed on the Back ſide of a ſcandalous Rhiming Libel upon his Sermon of Reſtitution, he is threatned in caſe he ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Biſhoprick, with the Fate of thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Uſurpers,</hi> Gregory <hi>and</hi> George <hi>of</hi> Cappadocia, <hi>who unjuſtly invaded the See of</hi> Alexandria <hi>upon the depoſing of</hi> Athanaſius, <hi>the Orthodox Biſhop there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Anſwer to this takes up the reſt of his Book, in which he takes a great deal of Pains (perhaps to little purpoſe) and makes many Flouriſhes, pretending to be very accurate, like a <hi>Man of Senſe,</hi> in diſtinguiſhing, and aſſigning the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the Caſe of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and that of our <hi>depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Biſhops,</hi> in which he ſpends 13 or 14 Pages. But all that he ſays may be anſwer'd in a very few Words. And granting him, if it will do him any good, (becauſe I do not love to wrangle where there is no need) what he ſays in his three firſt Paragraphs, Pag. 18, 19, 20, 21. where he pretends ſo clearly and accurately to ſtate the Caſe touching the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporation of the Church into the State in a Chriſtian Nation and Government,</hi> and the <hi>Supremacy of the Sovereign Power in all Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes,</hi> and the Extent of that <hi>Supremacy,</hi> Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, I ſay, what he ſays in this (excepting only in his Inſtance of <hi>depoſing Biſhops,</hi> who were never anciently depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in any <hi>Regular, Orthodox, Chriſtian State</hi> without conſulting <hi>a Synod of Biſhops,</hi> unleſs in Caſes of <hi>capital Crimes,</hi> for which the criminal <hi>Biſhop</hi> has forfeited his Eſtate and Life, and the <hi>Sovereign Power</hi> may proceed to a <hi>Decollation,</hi> which is a <hi>Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> with a Witneſs, and that without conſulting a <hi>Synod</hi> or <hi>Council</hi>) I ſhall only take notice of his Diſtinction in his fourth Paragraph, Pag. 21. <hi>We muſt diſtinguiſh,</hi> ſays he, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an Eccleſiaſtical and Canonical Depoſition of a Biſhop for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, or other Eccleſiaſtical Crimes; and a State Deprivation. The firſt,</hi> he ſays, <hi>concerns the Character, and Eccleſiaſtical Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; it is the Cenſure of the Church, which concerns him as a Biſhop; and when it is ratified and confirmed, not only by a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, or National Synod, but by a General Council, ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58049:8"/> Biſhop is no longer a Biſhop of the Catholick Church, and no Chriſtian muſt communicate with him as a Biſhop. But a State Deprivation does not concern the Character; ſuch a Man may be a Biſhop of the Catholick Church ſtill, if he do not f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll under Church Cenſures, for Hereſy or other Crimes; but it only concerns the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his Epiſcopal Authority in any Dioceſe within the Dominions of that State, or enjoying any Eccleſiaſtical Benefice in it.</hi> Under the <hi>firſt</hi> Branch of this Diſtinction our <hi>Author</hi> ranks the Caſe of St. <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> and the Caſe of our <hi>deprived Biſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ps</hi> under the <hi>ſecond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſorry that our <hi>Author,</hi> who, it ſeems, has <hi>uſed himſelf to good Senſe, as well as to ancient Canons,</hi> ſhould be ſo groſly out in his Hiſtory. For 'tis notori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was not condemn'd or depos'd for <hi>Hereſy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r other Eccleſiaſtical Crimes; the Charge againſt him was not of that Nature. But the <hi>Arian</hi> Faction, being inveterate Haters of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> for his reſolute and conſtant adhering to the Catholick and Orthodox Faith, and vehemently and effectually oppoſing and baffling their Heteredox and Pernitious Opinions, and Heretical Doctrines and Poſitions, (and particularly at the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> where he gave a mighty Blow to the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and wounded even to Death their great <hi>Goliah, Arius,</hi> which was not forgot when he was advanc'd to the Epiſcopal Throne) contriv'd his Ruin, and to that end they accuſe him to the <hi>Emperor</hi> (who, they knew, was ſenſible that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was Orthodox, and therefore that 'twas in vain to charge him with <hi>Hereſy</hi>) for being a <hi>turbulent, muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, factious Man,</hi> and a <hi>Diſturber of the Peace,</hi> and other <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moralities.</hi> The <hi>Emperor</hi> out of a juſt Veneration and Defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for his Character (the Crimes laid to his Charge not being <hi>Capital,</hi> which if they had, there would have been another ſort of Procedure againſt him; witneſs the <hi>Emperor</hi>'s Directions to <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Life of St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in <hi>Cave</hi>'s Lives of the Fathers, <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. p. 77.</note> 
               <hi>Dalmatius</hi> the Cenſor at <hi>Antioch</hi> to proceed againſt him upon a Charge of Murther, who accordingly gave him Notice to provide for his Tryal, but before the Day came the <hi>Emperor</hi> was ſatisfied that the Perſon, whom
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58049:8"/> he was accus'd by the <hi>Arians</hi> to have murther'd, was alive) conven'd a <hi>Synod,</hi> to which he referr'd the Examination of <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s Caſe, in which his implacable Enemies (whoſe Malice and Revenge was whetted and heightned to the higheſt degree) being both <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in the Synod at <hi>Tyre.</hi> Id. p. 87.</note> his <hi>Accuſers</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi> they ſoon pronounc'd him guilty of the Crimes, which he was moſt <note n="b" place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> appear before the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uncil of <hi>Sard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ca</hi> to be <hi>nothing but a Train of Malice and Villany.</hi> Id. p. 115.</note> unjuſtly charged with; and ſo depos'd him, not from the <hi>Epiſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pal Character,</hi> but <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> and the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of his See: Upon which the <hi>Emperor</hi> baniſh'd him.</p>
            <p>So that ſuch a Block-head as I am can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (whatever this Gentleman with his <hi>Linceus</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, <hi>who has uſed himſelf ſo much to good Senſe, as well as to ancient Canons,</hi> can) ſo <hi>eaſily perceive</hi> ſuch <hi>a vaſt Difference between theſe two Caſes.</hi> Were our <hi>deprived Biſhops</hi> charged with, or condemn'd for <hi>Hereſy?</hi> So neither was St. <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> Are our <hi>Biſhops</hi> depoſed from their <hi>Epiſcopal Character?</hi> So neither was St. <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> Are our <hi>Biſhops</hi> accus'd of, and depriv'd for an Offence againſt the <hi>State?</hi> So was St. <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> Are our <hi>Biſhops</hi> depoſed from their <hi>Epiſcopal Juriſdiction,</hi> and the <hi>Revenues of their Sees?</hi> So was St. <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</hi> Are our <hi>deprived Biſhops</hi> thruſt out and ſucceeded by <hi>Eccleſiaſtical, Schiſmatical</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <p>Such the <hi>Sardican</hi> Council eſteem'd the Anti Biſhops that were poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs'd of St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s See at <hi>Alexandria—Gregory</hi> is branded with this Mark of Infamy and Dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, p. 116.—<hi>but eſpecially in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sentence againſt</hi> Gregory <hi>the</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian <hi>Int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r at</hi> Alexandria, <hi>they ſhew'd a particular Deteſtation, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing him not only to have been no Biſhop, but not worthy the Name of a Chriſtian nulling all Ordinations made by him, and forbidding any to bear that Character, that had receiv'd Orders from him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>George,</hi> the <hi>Cappadocian</hi> Monſter, (as <hi>Nazienzen</hi> calls him,) who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Gregory</hi> was diſown'd and diſcountenanc'd by all the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, Suffragan Biſhops and Clergy belonging to the Metropolitical See of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> was inſtall'd by a military Guard, being indeed a Man of Blood; had a bloody Entrance, a bloody Continuance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a bloody Exit. <hi>Id.</hi> p. 142, 143. and p. 174, 175.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders and Uſurpers?</hi> So was St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> So that it does not appear that there is ſo <hi>vaſt a Difference between theſe two Caſes. i. e.</hi> in reſpect of the Matter and Nature of the Depoſition or Deprivation, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our <hi>Author's accurate</hi> Diſtinction. Indeed there is this Difference (which he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58049:9"/> may call <hi>a vaſt Difference,</hi> if he pleaſes) <hi>between theſe two Caſes,</hi> in reſpect of the Manner of the Procedure. <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> had the Juſtice done him of being heard and try'd, and had Liberty to anſwer for himſelf: But our <hi>Biſhops</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, <hi>indictâ cauſâ,</hi> without a formal Proceſs, unheard, untry'd, and without Liberty to anſwer for themſelves. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> had the Honour and Deference paid to his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, to have his Caſe referr'd to, and examin'd in a <hi>Synod.</hi> But our <hi>Biſhop's</hi> are <hi>unſynodically</hi> and <hi>uncanonically</hi> depoſed, and cenſur'd, and condemn'd by an illegal <hi>Convention. Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> was cenſur'd and condemn'd for a Crime, which (as 'twas ſuppoſed, though not proved) he <hi>had committed:</hi> But our <hi>Biſhops</hi> were cenſur'd and condemn'd not for a Crime <hi>paſt,</hi> but to <hi>come;</hi> not for a Fault that they <hi>bad committed,</hi> but for an Offence which 'twas expected they <hi>would be guilty of. Athanaſius</hi> liv'd under a more <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Government, and was Subject to the Will of an <hi>abſolute Prince;</hi> (who yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him the Favour cuſtomarily due to <hi>Chriſtian Biſhops</hi>) But our <hi>deprived Biſhops</hi> have the Happineſs to live in a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where they have a Right, in common with others, to the Benefit of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which provides that no <hi>Engliſh Subject</hi> ſhall loſe Life, Limb, or Eſtate for any Offence, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he is tryed by his Peers; which is the inalienable <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi> and <hi>Birth-Right</hi> of an <hi>Engliſh Subject.</hi> Which not a Lawyer in <hi>England</hi> will deny. But <q>
                  <l>—Video Meliora proboque,</l>
                  <l>Deteriora ſequor.—</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I am not, I thank God, either ſo Popiſh, or Fanatical as to deny that the <hi>Supreme Power</hi> has <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> over <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Perſons,</hi> who are Subject, as well as the Laity, to the Laws of diſtributive Juſtice, and that both in reſpect of <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Puniſhments.</hi> I will <hi>allow</hi> (to uſe our <hi>Author</hi>'s Words, Pag. 23.) <hi>the Supreme Power of a Nation to judge, who ſhall be Biſhops in their Dominions, and enjoy the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58049:9"/> of the Church, which are the Gift of the State;</hi> but, by his leave, not <hi>ſuch a Gift</hi> as is that of civil and military Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, of a <hi>Judge</hi> or a <hi>Captain,</hi> which they are to hold <hi>ad pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citum,</hi> or <hi>quam diu ſe bene geſſerint:</hi> but it is <hi>ſuch a Gift,</hi> as when once given, and legally ſettled on the Perſon on whom it is beſtow'd, cannot be arbitrarily taken away at pleaſure; it being for his <hi>Life,</hi> and as much his <hi>Free-hold,</hi> as any Land in <hi>England</hi> is the Purchaſers, who buys and pays for it. And then as for <hi>Puniſhments,</hi> there is no doubt but that <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Perſons</hi> of what Degree or Figure ſoever they be, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> who may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict Puniſhments according to the demerits of the Offenders. If the Crime is <hi>Capital,</hi> the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Perſon</hi> may be try'd, and (if found Guilty) condemn'd in a Court of Juſtice by Criminal Judges, without a <hi>Synod</hi> or <hi>Council.</hi> But if it be an Offence againſt the <hi>State</hi> of a leſſer and more inferiour Nature (as was that of St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) it has been uſual and cuſtomary, as I ſaid before, in Regular, Orthodox, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian States (I hope our <hi>Author</hi> will not inſiſt on the Inſtance of the <hi>Parliamentary Depoſition</hi> and <hi>Deprivation</hi> of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> in purſuance of the <hi>Holy Covenant,</hi> in the late <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> or rather <hi>Rebellion,</hi> (if it will not offend our <hi>Author</hi> to call it ſo) which was indeed a Depoſition of Biſhops without a <hi>Synod</hi> or <hi>Council,</hi> and which perhaps may be ſutably rankt under the ſecond Branch of his aforeſaid Diſtinction of a <hi>State-Deprivation</hi>) and that out of Deference to the Epiſcopal Character, to conſult a <hi>Synod</hi> or <hi>Council</hi> in caſe of the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition or Deprivation of Biſhops from their Epiſcopal Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and the Revenues of their Sees. And though the great Kindneſs and Indulgence of Chriſtian <hi>Emperors</hi> to Biſhops, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Cauſes</hi> (but not <hi>all Cauſes,</hi> as our <hi>Author</hi> falſly ſpeaks, without diſtinguiſhing between Offfences againſt the State, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Witneſs the intended and appointed Tryal of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> before <hi>Dalmatius</hi> the Cenſor at <hi>Antioch,</hi> as aforeſaid, and his Examination before the <hi>Emperor</hi> upon a Charge of High Treaſon) <hi>reſerving,</hi> I ſay, <hi>Cauſes relating to Biſhops to the Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. p. 76.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58049:10"/> 
               <hi>of their own Synods,</hi> was in proceſs of Time abuſed, and by Degrees grew into the <hi>Omnipotent Power of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome (as our <hi>Author</hi> ſpeaks, Pag. 26.) <hi>which domineered over Emperors themſelves, and ſet the Church above the State,</hi> yet the abuſe ought not to aboliſh the uſe of that which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, convenient, and laudable.</p>
            <p>But our <hi>Author</hi> ſeems to be one of them, who, <hi>out of their juſt Zeal againſt the Extravagantcies of thoſe who ſcrued up</hi> Church Power <hi>to ſo high a Peg, that it was thought to make per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iren. 2 Edit. with Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix. pag. 418. ſect. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Diſcord with the</hi> Common-wealth, <hi>could never think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves free from ſo great an Inconvenience, till they had melted down all</hi> Spiritual Power <hi>into the</hi> Civil State, <hi>and diſſolv'd the</hi> Church <hi>into the</hi> Commonwealth; to uſe the Words of the Learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet.</hi> Who, whatever might unadviſedly drop from his Pen, in his <hi>Irenicum,</hi> derogatory to the <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Privilege</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> (which might owe it ſelf to his <hi>Juvenile Heat,</hi> and too long and familiar Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with <hi>Eraſtian</hi> and <hi>Republican</hi> Principles, with which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps his <hi>Mind</hi> was <note n="*" place="margin">There is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a kind of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riety of the Mind, as well as of the Body, which makes it ſo u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtable and pendulous that it oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s from one Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry—So that whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they that at an Appari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo much d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o theſe untrodden P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hs, wherein they loſe both themſelves and the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p 418. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 418. ſect. 2.</note> 
               <hi>inebriated,</hi> which made him <hi>reel</hi> to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>Extreams</hi>) yet has honeſtly made Amends in his <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix,</hi> apologizing for himſelf in a lucky Parentheſis.—<hi>Which</hi> Hypotheſis, ſays he, <hi>is the only rational Foundation on which</hi> Epiſcopal <hi>Government in the</hi> Church <hi>doth ſtand firm and unſhaken, and which in the former Diſcourſe I am far from under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of, as an intelligent Reader may perceive.</hi>—And he muſt be a very <hi>intelligent Reader</hi> indeed that can perceive it. And therefore to expiate his Offence (which was <hi>taken,</hi> if not <hi>given</hi>) and prevent all Miſtakes, and undeceive and fully inform the leſs diſcerning, intelligent Reader, he ſpeaks plain in his <hi>Appendix</hi> (to which I will refer my <hi>Author</hi> for a fuller Anſwer to his <hi>accurate Diſtinction</hi> between an <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> and a <hi>State-Deprivation,</hi> in which perhaps, being the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of a <hi>great Man,</hi> he may acquieſce; and for the ſake of my Reader, who may not have the Book, I will tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a few remarkable Paſſages) wherein he t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls you, <hi>That the World may ſee he has not been more forward to aſſert the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58049:10"/> juſt Power of the Magiſtrate in</hi> Eccleſiaſticals, <hi>as well as</hi> Civils, <hi>than to defend the Fundamental</hi> Rights <hi>of the</hi> Church, <hi>he has taken this Opportunity more fully to explain and vindicate that part of the</hi> Churches-Power, <hi>which lies in reference to</hi> Offenders; <hi>and therefore endeavours to give the</hi> Church <hi>her due, as well as</hi> Ceſar <hi>his, by making good this following</hi> Principle <hi>or</hi> Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, <hi>viz. That the Power of inflicting Cenſures upon Offenders in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. ſect. 3.</note> 
               <hi>a Chriſtian Church, is a Fundamental Right, reſulting from the Conſtitution of the Church, as a Society by Jeſus Chriſt; and that the Seat of this Power is in thoſe Officers of the Church, who have derived their Power originally from the Founder of this Society, and act by virtue of the Laws of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In purſuance, and for the better Explanation of which <hi>Principle,</hi> he aſſerts, and endeavours to demonſtrate,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That the Church is a peculiar Society in its own Nature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 423. ſect. 10.</note> 
               <hi>diſtinct from the Common-wealth;</hi> and that <hi>by reaſon of its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution, diſtinct Officers, different Rights, and Ends, and peculiar Offences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That the Power of the Church over its Members in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 431. ſect. 17.</note> 
               <hi>caſe of Offences, doth not ariſe meerly from Confederation and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, though it doth ſuppoſe it. Which</hi> Power, ſays he, <hi>may be conſider'd two ways, either Firſt, as it implies the</hi> Right <hi>in ſome of</hi> inflicting Cenſures; <hi>as</hi> Excommunication, Suſpenſion, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>or</hi> Deprivation <hi>of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>For the <hi>Laity</hi> to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> or <hi>depoſe</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> is as prepoſterous, as for the <hi>Sheep</hi> to diſciplin the <hi>Shepherd.</hi> Even <hi>Nature</hi> teaches us, that if the <hi>Shepherd</hi> offends, he muſt be cenſur'd by his Fellow-<hi>Shepherds,</hi> and not by the <hi>Sheep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Even King <hi>James</hi> himſelf, as great a Violator of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> and the <hi>Privileges</hi> of <hi>Society,</hi> as he was vogu'd to be, did not think it proper to refer the <hi>Cenſure. i. e.</hi> the <hi>Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> or <hi>Deprivation</hi> of <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> to the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> or the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> but left it to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſioners</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Biſhops, &amp;c.</hi> who were fitteſt to cenſure their Brethren. They ſay, <hi>It is a Diamond that muſt cut a Diamond.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Officers, when there is juſt cauſe for it.</hi> Which are <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as ſuch, and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly relating to <hi>Church-Power,</hi> and not <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>State. For the</hi> Exerciſe <hi>and</hi> Adminiſtration <hi>of this</hi> Power, <hi>belongs not to the Body of the Society conſider'd</hi> complexly, <hi>but to the ſpecial</hi> Officers <hi>and</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors <hi>of the</hi> Church (<hi>who like the Eyes to the Body, are the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the</hi> Overſeers <hi>of it) none
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58049:11"/> elſe being capable of exerciſing this</hi> Power <hi>of the</hi> Church, <hi>as ſuch, but they on whom it is ſettled by the</hi> Founder <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>it ſelf. Or, Secondly, as it implies in others, the</hi> Duty of ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Cenſures inflicted. <hi>So that the</hi> Right <hi>of inflicting</hi> Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures<note place="margin">Pag. 437. ſect. 19</note> 
               <hi>doth not reſult meerly</hi> ex confederatâ diſcipliná, <hi>the</hi> Power <hi>being ſettled upon the Church by</hi> Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That this Power of the Church doth extend to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of Offenders from the Privileges of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>That the Fundamental Rights of the Church do not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. p 423. and 446.</note> 
               <hi>eſcheat to the Common-wealth, upon its being united or incorporated into a Chriſtian State. (Which</hi> Union <hi>or</hi> Incorporation, he ſays,<note place="margin">Pag. 446.</note> 
               <hi>is only accidental as to the Conſtitution of a Church) but the Power remains formally in the Church. Which</hi> Power, he ſays,<note place="margin">Pag. 422. ſect. 9.</note> 
               <hi>is not only a kind of</hi> Widows <hi>Eſtate, which belonged to it only du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring its Separation from the</hi> Civil Power, <hi>but the</hi> Church <hi>is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely infe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffed of it as its perpetual</hi> Right, <hi>belonging to it in all Conditions whatſoever it ſhould be in; as appears by the</hi> Tenure <hi>of it, and the</hi> Grounds <hi>on which it is conveyed, which being perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and univerſal, it from thence appears that no</hi> Acceſſion <hi>to the</hi> Church <hi>can invalidate its former</hi> Title.</p>
            <p>And then that <hi>Reverend Author</hi> concludes with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Paſſage, <hi>That though the Magiſtrate hath the main</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 447.</note> 
               <hi>Care of ordering Things in the Church</hi> (that is, in reſpect of <hi>the</hi> Right <hi>of Supreme Management of this</hi> Power <hi>in an external</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 446.</note> 
               <hi>way,</hi> of which he gives four particular Inſtances) <hi>yet (the Magiſtrate's Power in the Church being cumulative, and not pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative) the Church and her Officers retain the Fundamental Right of inflicting Cenſures on Offenders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What has been already ſaid is enough to anſwer what our <hi>Author</hi> does further urge, Pag. 27. touching the Authority which the <hi>Jewiſh Kings exerciſed over their High Prieſts,</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom 'tis very probable, and nothing appears to the contrary, that they conſulted the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi>) and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <hi>Solomon</hi>'s depoſing <hi>Abiathar,</hi> and placing <hi>Zadock</hi> in his ſtead. Let it be conſider'd what <hi>Abiathar</hi>'s Crime was, which (as appears by the Words he recites) was no leſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58049:11"/> than <hi>High Treaſon</hi> in following <hi>Adonijah</hi> to make him King, for which <hi>Solomon,</hi> inſtead of taking away his <hi>Place,</hi> might have taken off his <hi>Head,</hi> he having forfeited both his Eſtate and Life.</p>
            <p>As to what he ſays, Pag. 27. about the changing the <hi>High-Prieſt every Year (though by the Inſtitution of God it was for Life) when</hi> Judea <hi>was under the Government of the</hi> Romans, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive is nothing to the purpoſe; (the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Polity and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being diſſolv'd, and that according to the Will of God, in purſuance of the ancient Prediction, (<hi>Gen</hi> 49. 10.) and therefore no wonder that our <hi>Saviour</hi> was not concern'd at it, nor found fault with their Change either of their <hi>High-Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Kings.</hi>) And as impertinent is his Inſtance, Pag 28. of the <hi>Grand Signior's making and unmaking the Patriarch of</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>at pleaſure</hi> (to which he may add <hi>Oliver</hi>'s depoſing of Biſhops, and depriving the Divines of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> if he pleaſes, and ſo joyn a <hi>Mahometan</hi> and an <hi>Uſurper</hi>) notwithſtanding what Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> ſays (who, he tells us, in his Caſe of Allegiance took Notice of this as matter of Fact, without enquiring into the Reaſons) whoſe <hi>Authority</hi> is of as little Eſteem with me, as his own <hi>Principles</hi> are with himſelf.</p>
            <p>There remains but one Thing more which I ſhall take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and that is what our <hi>Author</hi> ſays, Pag. 29. <hi>The Truth is,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the ſame Objections which are now made againſt the Promotion of theſe new Biſhops, are equally ſtrong, and as eagerly urg'd at this Day by the Papiſts againſt our firſt Reformers: For they were promoted to Biſhopricks, while the former Popiſh Biſhops were living, and not canonically depoſed by any Act of the Church, but only by the Authority of the State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That the <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> in the Beginning of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (to which I preſume he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Fox</hi> Book of Martyrs, Vol. 3.</note> were ſummon'd by the Queen to meet in an Aſſembly of Divines conven'd at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to diſpute and debate about Matters of Religion, in order to the Settlement of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58049:12"/> 
               <hi>Church.</hi> But the <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> were contumacious, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous in the Aſſembly, and Diſturbers of the Peace, and would not pay Obedience to the Queens Orders and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections about the Method of the ſaid Diſputation and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. So that the Aſſembly was forc'd to break up without proſecuting or promoting the pious Ends for which they met. For which contumacy and Diſobedience they fell under the Queens Diſpleaſure, and were committed to Priſon; but were not depos'd, or depriv'd of their Biſhopricks by any Act of the State. Sometime after a <hi>Parliament</hi> was call'd, and Matters of Religion and the Government of the <hi>Church</hi> ſettled, and the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Worſhip aboliſhed. But the <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> would not qualifie themſelves to hold their Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks, but utterly refus'd to ſubſcribe to, or comply with the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as by Law eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Which is far wide from the Caſe of our <hi>deyrived Biſhops.</hi> What Contumacy, or mutinous Behaviour, or Diſobedience were they guilty of? Were they not ſufficiently qualified to hold their Biſhopricks according to the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> Were they Oppugners of the <hi>Doctrine, Diſcipline,</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> of it? On the contrary, Have they not been, and are they not ſtill zealous and conſtant Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Maintainers of it? For which they ſuffer, and for which in time they will have their Reward, if not in this World, yet in that to come; when their <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> without Repentance, will receive the Reward of their <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author</hi> concludes with deſiring his Friend to perſuade Dr. <hi>B—to repent, and puclickly to own his Miſtake.</hi>—Perhaps the <hi>Doctor</hi> has prevented him, and has repented ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, and does not think fit now to repent of his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance (which 'tis only to be wiſh'd he would make as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as his <hi>Error) which may not be too late to do himſelf good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only Recompence he can now make.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58049:12"/>
            <p>Thus, Sir, begging your Pardon for the Trouble of this Paper, which may ſerve a little to divert you in the <hi>Country,</hi> inſtead of better Entertainment, I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lond.</hi> 
                  <date>June 10. 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
